Register of the Scientists For Sakharov, Orlov And Shcharansky Records, 1975-2010
Hoover Institution Archives
Scientists For Sakharov, Orlov And Shcharansky Records
1975-2010
98007
Hoover Institution Archives
32 manuscript boxes, 2 oversize boxes, 1 card file boxes, 12 videotape cassettes, 3 phonotape cassettes (15 linear feet)
Correspondence, speeches and writings, reports, memoranda, press releases, statements, petitions, lists, financial records, printed matter, photographs, video tapes, and sound recordings, relating to civil rights and dissident scientists in the Soviet Union, and especially to Andrei Sakharov, Yuri Orlov and Anatoly Shcharansky (Natan Sharansky). Includes some papers of Morris Pripstein, chairman of the organization.
Scientists for Sakharov, Orlov and Shcharansky.
Access
Collection open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Historical Note
Scientists for Sakharov, Orlov and Shcharansky (SOS), formerly known as Scientists for Shcharansky, is a private non-governmental organization created by a group of physicists at the University of California, Berkeley. It came into existence in the summer of 1978 in response to the arrests of Yuri Orlov and Anatoly Shcharansky (later known as Natan Sharansky). There was a great deal of concern in the scientific community over the numerous violations of human rights affecting fellow scientists in many parts of the world. In the face of the seriously deteriorating plight of dissident scientist colleagues, the group felt the need to plot out a totally new course of action on behalf of their beleaguered colleagues, with the focus on the Soviet Union, but not exclusively so.
A guiding principle was to engage individual scientists to act collectively in unorthodox efforts to publicly "encourage" the Soviet authorities to cease their human rights violations,by making the violaters pay a price for their transgressions. Examples of such actions included an unprecedented moratorium on scientific cooperation with the Soviet Union, a "Hostages for Elena Bonner" initiative where prominent Western scientists volunteered to serve as good-faith witnesses in the Soviet Union during the temporary release of Sakharov's wife for medical treatment in the West, and picketing of embassies and of selected scientists at scientific conferences.
Within a short time, the SOS developed into a nationwide organization with a membership of 2,400 scientists including 13 Nobel laureates, 113 members of the U.S. National Academy of Sciences and presidents of 20 major scientific societies, all committed to a personal moratorium on scientific exchange with the Soviet Union. This action was quickly denounced in a major article in Pravda, commissioned by the Secretariat of the Central Committee of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union, which included K.U. Chernenko and M.S. Gorbachev, future General Secretaries.
After the Soviet scientist and Nobel laureate Andrei Sakharov was exiled to the city of Gorky in January 1980, SOS added his name and extended its moratorium campaign internationally. Within months, SOS grew into an international movement to promote the human rights of scientists, comprising more than 8,000 scientists from 44 countries.
As a result of the efforts of the U.S. government during the 1980s and the work of SOS, among others, Andrei Sakharov was freed from his internal exile and Yuri Orlov, after years in KGB prison and labor camp, was released from Siberian exile and deported to New York City in October 1986 as part of a swap that freed U.S. journalist Nicholas Daniloff and accused Soviet spy Gennadi Zakharov; he then went on to establish a successful academic career at Cornell University. Anatoly Shcharansky (Natan Sharansky), who was imprisoned by the KGB for his work on behalf of the Jewish emigration movement was also released in 1986 and settled in Israel where he served for awhile as Minister of Industry and Trade in the government.
As promised in its moratorium pledge, SOS disbanded after the three scientists were freed.
Scope and Content Note
The Scientists for Sakharov, Orlov and Shcharansky collection in the Hoover Institution Archives was donated in 1998 by Morris Pripstein, professor of physics at the University of California, Berkeley, and a founding member of SOS, on the 20th anniversary of the founding of SOS. It consists mainly of the organization's correspondence and administrative records (see General Office File), as well as records of other organizations involved with the issues of human rights and writings of individual scientists (see Subject File). There is also a large volume of correspondence of the chairman of SOS, Dr. Morris Pripstein, with scientists and activists representing various universities and organizations (see Chairman's File). Finally, the audio-visual part of the collection forms a complementary addition to the records of SOS.
General note
Scientists for Sakharov, Orlov and Shcharansky will be abbreviated throughout as SOS
Orlov, Yuri, 1924-; Sakharov, Andreĭ, 1921-; Shcharansky, Anatoly.; United States--Foreign relations.; Dissenters--Soviet Union.; Human rights--Soviet Union.; Phonotapes.; Russia (Federation); Scientists--Soviet Union.; Scientists--United States.; Soviet Union.; Video tapes.
- General Office File, 1978-1989
  Scope and Contents note
  Addresses, agreements, articles, brochures, bulletins, clippings, financial records, flyers, guest book, lists, maps, memoranda, messages, minutes of meetings, newsletters, notes, outline, documents relating to the origin, development, and future goals of the Scientists for Sakharov, Orlov and Shcharansky, postal records, press releases, printed matter, programs, proposals, remarks, reports, schedule, signatures, speeches, statements, statistical records, telegrams, testimony, travel records, and miscellany, either issued or received by SOS, relating to the activities of SOS, arranged alphabetically by physical form
  - General (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Address given at the anniversary meeting of the Royal Society by President Andrew Huxley, 1982 November 30 (Folder 2)
  - Agreements on scientific and technical cooperation, including cooperation in the exploration and use of outer space for peaceful purposes, between the National Academy of Sciences of the United States and the Academy of Sciences of the Soviet Union (Folder 3)
  - Articles (Folder 4)
  - Brochures (Folder 5)
  - Bulletins (Folder 6)
  - Clippings (Folder 7-8)
  - Financial records
    - General
      - General (Folder 9)
      - Agreements. Includes an agreement relating to the Washington Research Institute grant to the SOS (Folder 10)
      - Bank statements
        - 1978-1980 (Folder 11)
        - 1981-1984 (Box 2, Folder 1-2)
        - 1985-1986 (Folder 3)
      - Bills (Box 3)
        - Payment records for bills (Folder 1)
        - Telephone bill statements (Folder 2)
      - Budget (Folder 3)
      - Checkbook (Folder 4)
      - Correspondence (Folder 5)
      - Deposit and debit slips (Folder 6)
      - Invoices (Folder 7)
      - Memoranda (Folder 8)
      - Notes (Folder 9)
      - Receipts (Folder 10)
      - Reports (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Gottfried, Kurt, member, SOS Executive Committee. See also Chairman's File and Subject File (Folder 2)
    - Robinson, Louis G. (Folder 3)
    - Miscellany (Folder 4)
  - Flyers (Folder 5)
  - Guest book (Folder 6)
  - Lists
    - General
      - General
        - General (Folder 7)
        - Address - United States (Folder 8)
        - Distribution (Folder 9)
        - Fund-raising (Folder 10)
        - Mailing (Folder 11)
        - Membership
          - General (Folder 12)
          - Directory of key forum members (Folder 13)
        - Pledge
          - Cancelled envelopes (Folder 14)
          - Moratorium pledge lists (Folder 15)
          - Moratorium pledge lists (Box 5, Folder 1-2)
        - Press (Folder 3)
        - Signatures by institution (Folder 4)
      - Affiliates - United Kingdom (Folder 5)
      - Contributors (Folder 6)
      - Fellows of Royal Society of London (Folder 7)
      - Guarantors
        - United Kingdom (Folder 8)
        - United States (Folder 9)
      - Hostage-exchange volunteers (Folder 10)
      - Internees (Folder 11)
      - Invitees (Folder 12)
      - Participants in a tutorial (Folder 13)
      - Professional societies (Folder 14)
      - Scientists and scholars
        - General (Folder 15)
        - List of Refusenik scientists from Moscow (Box 6, Folder 1)
        - List of scientists and scholars compiled for United Nations dinner (Folder 2)
      - Sponsors (Folder 3)
      - Volunteers (Folder 4)
    - Countries
      - General (Folder 5)
      - Italy (Folder 6)
  - Map of freedom created by Freedom House, of Moscow subway, of University of California at Berkeley campus, and of Washington, D.C. (Folder 7)
  - Memoranda, Inter-office
    - Undated (Folder 8)
    - 1978-1979 (Folder 9)
    - 1980-1981 (Folder 10)
    - 1982 (Folder 11)
    - 1983-1987 (Folder 12)
  - Messages (telephone and Soviet radio broadcast messages sent to SOS) (Folder 13)
  - Minutes of meetings
    - Includes advice to organizers of international scientific meetings, Undated. (Folder 14)
    - 1978-1986 (Folder 15)
  - Newsletters (Folder 16)
  - Notes by SOS and others on meetings, Congressional trip to the Soviet Union, and various subjects (Folder 17)
  - Policy file
    - General
      - General (Folder 18)
      - Section I (Folder 19)
      - Section I (Box 7, Folder 1)
      - Section II (Folder 2-3)
      - Section III (Folder 4-5)
      - Section IV (Folder 6)
    - Declarations of principle
      - Undated (Folder 7-8)
      - 1978-1979 (Folder 9)
    - Discussion papers on program goals and future plans (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Initiatives (Folder 2)
    - Organizational records (Folder 3)
    - Petitions (Folder 4)
    - Position paper (Folder 5)
    - Statements of conscience
      - Undated (Folder 6-7)
      - 1978-1979 (Folder 8)
      - Miscellany (Folder 9)
  - Postal records (Folder 10)
  - Press releases (Box 9)
    - Undated (Folder 1)
    - 1978-1988 (Folder 2)
  - Press coverage records (Folder 3)
  - Printed matter issued and collected by SOS (Folder 4-7)
  - Printed matter issued and collected by SOS (Box 10)
  - Printed matter issued and collected by SOS (Box 11, Folder 1-6)
  - Proposals for assistance to the Charitable Society Miloserdiye in the Soviet Union, the Freedom of Communications Committee, and the SALT debate (Folder 7)
  - Remarks. Includes remarks made by Tom Harkin, Harold C. Hollenbeck, and Andrei Tverdokhlebov (Folder 8)
  - Reports. Includes reports prepared by A. Alexandrov, Bernard R. Cooper, Paul Kessler, Harry M. Scoble, Laurie S. Wiseberg, and progress report on SOS activities (Box 12)
    - Undated (Folder 1)
    - 1977-1980 (Folder 2)
    - 1981-1987 (Folder 3)
  - Schedule of events for scientists of SOS and other groups (Folder 4)
  - Speech for the defense of Victor Brailovskii at the Moscow Municipal Court session, 1981 June 18 (Folder 5)
  - (translated from Russian)
  - Statements
    - Undated (Folder 6)
    - 1978-1979 (Folder 7)
    - 1980-1988 (Folder 8)
  - Statistical records for exchange of individuals under the bilateral agreements between the United States and the Soviet Union, 1979-1981 (Folder 9)
  - Telegrams
    - Undated (Folder 10)
    - 1978-1982 (Folder 11)
    - 1983-1987 (Folder 12)
  - Travel file
    - General (Folder 13)
    - Instructions for scientists when traveling abroad (Folder 14)
    - Reports on various trips prepared by Bernard R. Cooper, E. Gerjuoy, Dorothy Hirsch, and Dennis Keefe (Folder 15)
    - Miscellany (Folder 16)
  - Miscellany (Folder 17)
- Correspondence, 1978-1997
  Individual and organizational correspondence arranged alphabetically by correspondent
  - General (Box 13)
    - Undated (Folder 1)
    - Mostly circular letters, including to Leonid I. Brezhnev, Konstantin U. Chernenko, and Helmut Schmidt, 1979-1986. (Folder 2)
  - Unidentified (Folder 3)
  - American Association for the Advancement of Science, 1979 (Folder 4)
  - American Jewish Committee, 1980 (Folder 5)
  - Australian Association for Cultural Freedom, 1980 (Folder 6)
  - Bertrand Russell Society, Inc., 1983 (Folder 7)
  - Binnie, B. M., 1984 (Folder 8)
  - Brandt, Willy, 1981 (Folder 9)
  - Braver, Lisa, 1978 (Folder 10)
  - California Institute of Technology, 1984 (Folder 11)
  - Carnegie Institution of Washington, 1984 (Folder 12)
  - CERN, 1992 (Folder 13)
  - Clinical Research Centre, 1980 (Folder 14)
  - Cockerell, Christopher, 1984 (Folder 15)
  - Cohen, Hyman, R., 1980 (Folder 16)
  - Columbia University, 1981 (Folder 17)
  - Cornell University, 1984 (Folder 18)
  - Cowling, T. G., 1984 (Folder 19)
  - Farella, Braun & Martel, 1982-1985 (Folder 20)
  - Freeman, Fox & Partners, 1984 (Folder 21)
  - Fried, Frank, Harris, Shriver & Kampelman, 1984 (Folder 22)
  - Gidal, George, 1979 (Folder 23)
  - Gutstein, Y., 1984 (Folder 24)
  - Harris, John L., 1980 (Folder 25)
  - Harvard Medical School, 1984 (Folder 26)
  - Harvard University, 1984 (Folder 27)
  - H.E.J. Postgraduate Institute of Chemistry, 1980 (Folder 28)
  - Hoover Institution On War, Revolution and Peace, 1982 (Folder 29)
  - Hottel, Hoyt C., 1984 (Folder 30)
  - Institute for Advanced Study, 1984 (Folder 31)
  - Instituto de Quimica Fisica Rocasolano, 1984 (Folder 32)
  - Instituto de Pesquisas Espaciais, 1984 (Folder 33)
  - International League against Rheumatism, 1980 (Folder 34)
  - Jon B. Jolly, Inc., 1979 (Folder 35)
  - Kolthoff, I. M., 1980 (Folder 36)
  - Lilienstern, Jan, 1980 (Folder 37)
  - McGill University, 1997 (Folder 38)
  - Massachusetts Institute of Technology, 1981-1984 (Folder 39)
  - Medical Research Council, 1984 (Folder 40)
  - Mindlin, Ivan, 1984 (Folder 41)
  - Nation, 1981 (Folder 42)
  - National Atomic Energy Agency, 1984 (Folder 43)
  - National Research Council, 1984 (Folder 44)
  - National University of Athens, 1980 (Folder 45)
  - New York Academy of Sciences, 1979 (Folder 46)
  - Public Interest Law Center of Philadelphia, 1980 (Folder 47)
  - Sciaky Bros. Inc., 1980 (Folder 48)
  - Shoppee, Charles W., 1980 (Folder 49)
  - Silver, Ronald, n.d. (Folder 50)
  - Southeastern Massachusetts University, 1980 (Folder 51)
  - Stanford University Medical Center, 1984 (Folder 52)
  - United States. Congress. Senate, 1979 (Folder 53)
  - United States. Department of State, 1979 (Folder 54)
  - United States. Department of the Treasury, 1985 (Folder 55)
  - Universidad del Valle de Guatemala, 1984 (Folder 56)
  - Université de Lausanne, 1980 (Folder 57)
  - University Chemical Laboratory, Cambridge, 1984 (Folder 58)
  - University of California, Berkeley, 1978 (Folder 59)
  - University of California, Davis, 1984 (Folder 60)
  - University of California, San Diego, 1984 (Folder 61)
  - University of Chicago, 1984 (Folder 62)
  - University of Delaware, 1980 (Folder 63)
  - University of East Anglia, 1984 (Folder 64)
  - University of London, 1980 (Folder 65)
  - University of Minnesota, 1984 (Folder 66)
  - University of Pennsylvania, 1984 (Folder 67)
  - University of Toronto, Sunnybrook Medical Center, 1980 (Folder 68)
  - University of Wisconsin, McArdle Laboratory, 1984 (Folder 69)
  - Upsala College, 1980 (Folder 70)
  - Washington University, n.d. (Folder 71)
  - Worcester Foundation for Experimental Biology, 1984 (Folder 72)
  - Yale University, 1984 (Folder 73)
- Chairman's File, 1978-1997.
  Materials related to activities of SOS Chairman Morris Pripstein. Includes appeals, articles, brochures, bulletins, clippings, correspondence, financial records, flow charts, flyers, lists, memoranda, messages, minutes of meetings, newsletters, notes, press releases, printed matter, remarks, reports, speeches, statements, telegrams, travel records, and miscellany, either issued or received by Morris Pripstein relating to his activities as Chairman of SOS, arranged alphabetically by physical form
  - Appeal to governments on behalf of Andrei Sakharov (possibly issued by Morris Pripstein) (Box 13, Folder 74)
  - Articles written by Morris Pripstein (Folder 75)
  - Brochures (Folder 76)
  - Bulletins (Folder 77)
  - Clippings (Folder 78)
  - Correspondence
    - General
      - Undated (Folder 79)
      - 1978-1986 (Folder 80)
    - Unidentified (Folder 81)
    - ABC News, 1983 (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Academia Nazionale dei Lincei, 1986-1989 (Folder 2)
    - Academic Committee on Soviet Jewry, 1979 (Folder 3)
    - Academy of Sciences of the USSR, 1979-1981 (Folder 4)
      Includes a resolution of the Central Committee for the publication of an article in Pravda in response to the first SOS initiative, 3 April 1979
    - Access to Energy, 1979 (Folder 5)
    - Action Courier Service, 1985 (Folder 6)
    - Action for Soviet Jewry, Inc., 1980-1982 (Folder 7)
    - Adair, ?, 1978 (Folder 8)
    - Adomato, Brian, 1980 (Folder 9)
    - Adoptieprogramma van Medici voor Slachtoffers van de Effecten van het Refusnikisme (AMSER), 1979-1981 (Folder 10)
    - Alekseyeva, Liza, Includes a statement from Andrei Sakharov, 1979-1982. (Folder 11)
    - Alfred University, 1982 (Folder 12)
    - American Academy of Arts and Sciences, 1984-1986 (Folder 13)
    - American Association for the Advancement of Science, 1979-1986 (Folder 14)
    - American Bar Association, 1985 (Folder 15)
    - American Enterprise Institute, 1979 (Folder 16)
    - American Institute of Physics, 1980-1986 (Folder 17)
    - American Jewish Committee, 1980-1986 (Folder 18)
    - American Physical Society, 1980-1985 (Folder 19)
    - American University, 1978-1987 (Folder 20)
    - Amnesty International, 1984 (Folder 21)
    - Andrei Sakharov Defense Campaign, 1980 (Folder 22)
    - Andrei Sakharov Institute, 1984 (Folder 23)
    - APS Committee on International Freedom of Scientists, 1980-1984 (Folder 24)
    - Argonne National Laboratory, 1982-1986 (Folder 25)
    - Armenian Academy of Sciences, 1981 (Folder 26)
    - Association for Computing Machinery, 1978-1980 (Folder 27)
    - AT&T Bell Laboratoratories, 1978-1986 (Folder 28)
    - Audiências Sakharov, 1983 (Folder 29)
    - Australian Association for Cultural Freedom, 1980 (Folder 30)
    - Australian Committee for Human Rights in the Soviet Union and Eastern Europe, 1979-1980 (Folder 31)
    - Australian National University, 1984 (Folder 32)
    - Azbel, Mark, 1981 (Folder 33)
    - Backus, John, 1984 (Folder 34)
    - Baltimore Jewish Community Relations Council, 1980 (Folder 35)
    - Barton, Mark G., 1979 (Folder 36)
    - Bay Area Council on Soviet Jewry, 1978-1986 (Folder 37)
    - BBC, 1979 (Folder 38)
    - Benson, Sidney W., 1982 (Folder 39)
    - Bernstein, Arthur, 1977-1978 (Folder 40)
    - Berresford Arms Hotel, 1982 (Folder 41)
    - Betty Lee Drugs, 1980 (Folder 42)
    - Bonner, Elena, Includes Morris Pripstein's letter addressed to both Elena Bonner and Andrei Sakharov. See also Subject File, 1985-1991. (Folder 43)
    - Book, David, n.d. (Folder 44)
    - Boruszewski, Wolodymir, 1984 (Folder 45)
    - Brandeis University, 1978 (Folder 46)
    - Breber, George, 1981 (Folder 47)
    - Breen, Marvin, Mr. and Mrs., 1979 (Folder 48)
    - Brezhnev, Leonid, 1979-1981 (Folder 49)
    - Brookhaven National Laboratory, 1979 (Folder 50)
    - Bulletin of Atomic Scientists, 1979 (Folder 51)
    - Cahn, Robert, 1986-1989 (Folder 52)
    - California Institute of International Studies, 1980 (Folder 53)
    - California Institute of Technology, 1978-1983 (Folder 54)
    - Canadian Committee of Scientists and Scholars, 1985 (Folder 55)
    - Carleton University, 1984 (Folder 56)
    - Carnegie-Mellon University, 1978-1984 (Folder 57)
    - Carter, Jimmy, 1986 (Folder 58)
    - Case Western Reserve University, 1978 (Folder 59)
    - Center for Appeals for Freedom, 1980-1982 (Folder 60)
    - Center for Peace and Freedom, 1986 (Folder 61)
    - Center for Russian Jewry with Student Struggle for Soviet Jewry, 1979 (Folder 62)
    - Cerin, Elmer, 1985 (Folder 63)
    - CERN, 1978-1987 (Folder 64)
    - Chamberlain, Owen, 1981 (Folder 65)
    - Chanowitz, Michael S., 1986-1987 (Folder 66)
    - Charap, John, 1980-1986 (Folder 67)
    - Chemical & Engineering News, 1978-1989 (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - Chernenko, Konstantin U., 1984 (Folder 2)
    - Chicago Action for Soviet Jewry, 1979 (Folder 3)
    - Clinical Research Centre, 1984 (Folder 4)
    - Chicago Tribune, 1979 (Folder 5)
    - Christian Science Monitor, 1978 (Folder 6)
    - Chronicle of Higher Education, 1980 (Folder 7)
    - City University of New York, 1980-1985 (Folder 8)
    - Cline, ?, 1979 (Folder 9)
    - Clogston, Albert M., 1979 (Folder 10)
    - Cohen, Jack, 1978-1980 (Folder 11)
    - Colgate, Rosemary W., 1980 (Folder 12)
    - College de France, 1982-1984 (Folder 13)
    - College of Arts and Sciences, 1989 (Folder 14)
    - Columbia University, 1981-1985 (Folder 15)
    - Commission on Security and Cooperation in Europe, See also Subject File, 1979-1988. (Folder 16)
    - Committee for the Bilateral Nuclear Weapons and Human Rights Declaration, 1984 (Folder 17)
    - Committee of Concerned Scientists, 1978-1983 (Folder 18)
    - Cornell University, 1979-1985 (Folder 19)
    - Cosmos Club, 1980 (Folder 20)
    - Courant, Ernest D., 1980 (Folder 21)
    - Daily Californian, 1984 (Folder 22)
    - Dartmouth College, 1978 (Folder 23)
    - Debreu, Gerard, 1978 (Folder 24)
    - Dickson, Lawrence J., 1979 (Folder 25)
    - Drell, Sidney David, 1981-1984 (Folder 26)
    - Eberhard, Alide, 1978 (Folder 27)
    - École Polytechnique (Palaiseau, France), 1978 (Folder 28)
    - Editions Frontières, 1991 (Folder 29)
    - EG&G, 1979-1980 (Folder 30)
    - Electrochemical Society, 1979 (Folder 31)
    - Erasmus Universiteit Rotterdam, 1979 (Folder 32)
    - Fainberg, V. Ya., 1979-1991 (Folder 33)
    - Federation of American Scientists, 1979-1988 (Folder 34)
    - Feldman, Jack, 1986 (Folder 35)
    - Ferbel, Tom, n.d. (Folder 36)
    - Flory, Emily J., See also Subject File, 1985-1986. (Folder 37)
    - Foreman, Lillian, 1984 (Folder 38)
    - Frank, Walter, 1980 (Folder 39)
    - Freedom of Communications, 1984-1989 (Folder 40)
    - Freedom House, 1980-1985 (Folder 41)
    - Fridjonsson, Siqurdur, 1980 (Folder 42)
    - Fried, Frank, Harris, Shriver & Kampelman, 1980-1982 (Folder 43)
    - Fund for Free Expression, 1980-1981 (Folder 44)
    - George Washington University, 1984 (Folder 45)
    - Gergely, Tomas, and Juan Méndez, 1982 (Folder 46)
    - Gidwitz, Betsy, 1979 (Folder 47)
    - Gilmore, Robert, 1979 (Folder 48)
    - Ginsberg, Barbara & Howard, 1982 (Folder 49)
    - Granit, Ragnar, 1984 (Folder 50)
    - Greek Atomic Energy Commission, 1980 (Folder 51)
    - Guttman, Frank, 1982 (Folder 52)
    - Hagedorn, ?, 1980 (Folder 53)
    - Harvard Medical School, 1979 (Folder 54)
    - Harvard University, 1985-1990 (Folder 55)
    - Heicklen, Julian, 1979 (Folder 56)
    - Helsinki Commission, 1980-1984 (Folder 57)
    - Helsinki Watch, See also Subject File, 1979-1986. (Folder 58)
    - Heriot-Watt University, 1984 (Folder 59)
    - Herzberg Institute of Astrophysics, 1983 (Folder 60)
    - Hook, Sidney, 1985 (Folder 61)
    - Hoover Institution On War, Revolution and Peace, 1982 (Folder 62)
    - Horn, ?, 1986 (Folder 63)
    - Hornstein, John, 1979 (Folder 64)
    - Horodysky, Daniel, 1985 (Folder 65)
    - Human Rights and Nuclear Weapons Committee, 1984 (Folder 66)
    - Hungarian Academy of Sciences, 1984 (Folder 67)
    - Huygens Laboratorium, 1984 (Folder 68)